Okay, so let's cover some motivational
theories.
Since there are some theories
that might be asked about
on the exam, so we've got
a couple of videos on these.
In this video, we're going to cover four
of the important motivational theories
that you need to know, again, for the PMP
exam.
Now, the first theory I want to talk about
is this one called
expectancy theory, right?
By someone by the name of Victor Vroom.
And again, wherever there's a name,
you need to know these names as well.
Now, what expectancy
theory refers to is the fact that
people are motivated by
certain expectation, right?
A particular action will lead to a
particular outcome, right?
So employees are going
to be motivated or, either or
they could just be indifferent
based on the expectation.
So, for example, it's like saying, if I
perform really well,
I'm going to get a bonus.
It's this expectation of a bonus that is
really motivating you.
to do a good job.
So, for example, a salesperson.
If you make this sale, if you close this
sale, you're going to have this bonus.
They're going to make a big bonus.
And so it's an expectation of a bonus
that's really motivating you.
As opposed to, what's the point of me
putting in long hours?
Right?
I'm doing all this work.
I'm putting in long hours and I'm not
going to get rewarded for it.
So why am I even doing this?
Well, you might still put in long hours.
But I'm, to do the work because you have
to, right?
You know, just to get the work finished,
you have to put in those long hours.
But you're not really motivated.
And there's a big difference between
someone that's motivated to do the work
rather than someone that's just doing it
to get a paycheck.
So an employee that is more motivated is
obviously going to do a much better job
than someone that just wants to do,
just doing it for the sake of doing it,
just to complete the work.
So obviously, you're just going to do it.
You know, you want to, so this then goes
to the employer, right?
You want to find ways of motivating.
So, employer or the manager or the leader,
right, you want to motivate
your team members.
Now, again, with any of these
theories, right, each of these
guys wrote books and sometimes
several books on their theories.
We are just covering the very,
very high level, right?
Basically, almost like a one-line summary.
You don't need to know a huge amount of
detail for the PMP.
exam on these.
All right, now the next theory
I want to cover is this one
called hygiene theory by
someone called Frederick Herzberg.
Now, hygiene theory, nothing to do with
personal cleanliness here.
This is to do with satisfiers and
dissatisfiers, motivators, motivators.
And the best way to explain this really is
to give you an example.
Now, think of your base income,
your base salary.
That in itself might not necessarily be a
huge motivator for you
to go above and beyond.
That's just your minimum expectation.
If you change jobs,
you get a slight salary
increase, again, that's
your minimum expectation.
Let's say at the end of the year,
you'll get a 1% pay raise.
You're not going to
suddenly start jumping up and
down in excitement because
I've got this 1% pay raise.
But what if you've got a 1% pay cut?
cut, that would definitely demotivate you,
right?
You would not be very happy.
So a salary then is what Herzberg would
consider a hygiene factor.
So salary is a hygiene factor according to
Herzberg.
Basically, the fact that you have a salary
doesn't necessarily motivate you,
but take part of it away and it will
definitely demotivate you.
So one of the things amongst many,
many things.
One of the things that Herzberg was
addressing here was the employer.
As an employer, you
may have all of these great
perks and benefits,
but just be very careful.
That becomes the minimum expectation.
If you have to start taking away some of
these benefits, then your employees are
going to be demotivated, they're going to
be demoralized, right?
because, you know, you're sort of taking
benefits away from them.
Regardless of whether or not those perks
and benefits are available in other,
you know, organizations, that's
irrelevant.
So basically, you're better off not
offering something in the first place
rather than offering something and then
taking it away.
That's even worse.
Then you have McClelland, David
McClelland.
He came up with what's known as a theory
of needs.
And what McClelland is saying is,
everyone has these three basic needs.
Achievement need, affiliation need,
and a power need.
Everyone has these three basic needs.
Achievement, affiliation and power,
all at varying degrees.
So let's talk about an extreme example of
each one.
So someone that has the
high achievement need,
an extreme example or
a high achievement need.
So these are literally people that are
overachievers.
Their entire life is their job.
Their job is their life.
That's all they care about.
right, but they have this one goal and
they need to achieve this goal.
Whatever that goal is, you know, at
all costs, they have to achieve this goal.
It doesn't matter that
the world is falling apart
around them, they
have to achieve this goal.
But they're self-motivated, they don't
like to see a job half done, right?
They like to see continuous improvement.
That would be more of the achievement
need.
Then you have an affiliation need.
So an extreme example or someone with a
high affiliation need, right?
These are people that care about
consensus.
They care about people around them,
right?
They want to make people happy.
Their decision making is based on whether
or not they're going to be popular, right?
They want to be popular
amongst their peers,
amongst their superiors,
amongst their subordinates.
They want to make everyone happy.
They want everyone to be happy with them.
And they need people around them to make
decisions.
And then you have the power need,
the extreme power need, right,
or someone with a high power need.
And I'm sure you can guess who they are.
They're your office bullies, right?
All they care about is being in charge,
right?
They're, you know, they're very
competitive.
They'll pull you down to try and get to
the top type of thing.
Right, they will, you know, they're
demeaning.
They always want the last word and so on
and so forth.
Now, what McClellan is saying is everyone
has each of these three, right,
each of these three traits or,
of needs, achievement, affiliation,
power at varying degrees.
Now, someone that has the edge towards the
achievement need, and not the extreme
example, more of the edge
towards achievement need,
they actually make the
best leaders, right, and why?
Because they have a goal.
They want to achieve this goal.
They're going to make decisions to achieve
this goal.
And this goal then is basically their
organization.
They're looking at the
organization, Look at
the strategic direction
of the organisation.
And so a good leader is someone
that is going to make decisions
and what's best for the
organisation that they're leading
rather than what's
best for them personally.
They have this goal for the organization.
They're making a decision for the
organization.
They usually make the best leaders, those
who have the edge
towards achievement need.
And in fact, those that have
the edge towards affiliation
need, they don't actually
make the best leaders.
And why?
Because, well, as a leader, you need to
make tough decisions.
Someone that has more of the affiliation
need, they find it hard to make tough
decisions because they're always trying to
make everyone happy.
They find it difficult to make tough
decisions.
So they don't always make the best
leaders.
As a leader, you always have to be prepared
to make some tough decisions there.
And then you've got Fiedler's contingency
theory, right, by this
guy called Fred Fiedler.
And I mean, he's basically saying there's
no single method of leadership, right?
Leaders adjust to the situation,
right?
Effective leadership is
contingent on matching the
leaders, the leader's
style to the actual setting.
Right.
So different types of
leaders are going to be
successful in different
types of situation.
For example, is it a stressful situation?
Is it a stressful organization,
a stressful industry?
or is it something more slow and laid
back?
So different leaders are going to be,
are going to strive in, you know,
in different locations or rather in
different situations.
Right, some leaders are not going
to strive in a stressful situation, right?
Some people are not going to strive in
that.
Whereas some people will not strive if
it's something, you know, an organization
that's more laid back and, you know,
slow moving.
Some people don't like that either.
So everybody is different.
And really, and all of these theories,
actually, all these are big huge theories.
I'm just giving you a very, very high
level, you know, high level summary.
So what Fiedler contingency theory is
basically saying that, you know,
all leadership styles are different.
And you need to place the right leader,
the right manager, in the right situation,
in the right saying.